<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>chip-seq on Not A Rocket Scientist</title>
    <link>https://dbrg77.github.io/tags/chip-seq/</link>
    <description>Recent content in chip-seq on Not A Rocket Scientist</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 17 May 2024 15:07:53 +0800</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://dbrg77.github.io/tags/chip-seq/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>ChIP Primer Design</title>
      <link>https://dbrg77.github.io/posts/2024-05-17-chip-primer-design/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 May 2024 15:07:53 +0800</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dbrg77.github.io/posts/2024-05-17-chip-primer-design/</guid>
      <description>When we study the functions of a gene of interest (GOI), it is common to use a combination of loss-of-function and gain-of-function assays in a study. In the era of genomics, we often use RNA-seq experiments to find out the affected genes when the level of the GOI is reduced, e.g. siRNA, shRNA &amp;amp; degron, or elevated e.g. over-expression. If the GOI is a transcription factor (TF), a special type of proteins that can specifically interact with DNA to regulate transcription, the natural question to ask is whether those affected genes are regulated directly by the TF.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Why do I like CUT&amp;RUN more than ChIP-seq</title>
      <link>https://dbrg77.github.io/posts/2018-10-23-why-do-i-like-cut-and-run-more-than-chip-seq/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dbrg77.github.io/posts/2018-10-23-why-do-i-like-cut-and-run-more-than-chip-seq/</guid>
      <description>Chromatin immunoprecipitation (ChIP) is one of the gold standards to study protein-DNA interaction in vivo. In 1984, John Lis&amp;rsquo; lab at Cornell invented the first ChIP method using UV to crosslink protein to DNA, and they used this approach to study the interaction of the RNA polymerase with specific genes (Gilmour and Lis, 1984). However, UV crosslinking causes DNA damage that makes cerntain downstream analysis, such as PCR, very difficult. Most people often choose to use another approach developed by Alexander Varshavsky&amp;rsquo;s lab later in 1988 at MIT, where they used formaldehyde for the crosslinking to study the histone-DNA interaction around the hsp70 gene (Solomon et al.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
