<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>ATAC-Seq on Not A Rocket Scientist</title><link>http://localhost:1313/tags/atac-seq/</link><description>Recent content in ATAC-Seq on Not A Rocket Scientist</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-gb</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 23 Jul 2024 09:00:00 +0800</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/atac-seq/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Understanding The Chromap Summary File</title><link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-07-23-understanding-the-chromap-summary-file/</link><pubDate>Tue, 23 Jul 2024 09:00:00 +0800</pubDate><guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-07-23-understanding-the-chromap-summary-file/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="background">Background&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>When talking about scATAC-seq data preprocessing, I guess the first method that most people choose is &lt;a href="https://support.10xgenomics.com/single-cell-atac/software/overview/welcome">&lt;strong>Cell Ranger ATAC&lt;/strong>&lt;/a>. The 10x Genomics Single Cell ATAC kit is probably the most widely used commercial method for doing scATAC-seq, and &lt;strong>Cell Ranger ATAC&lt;/strong> provides a very convenient way of converting the raw sequencing reads to some sort of count matrix for downstream in-depth analyses. The problems with &lt;strong>Cell Ranger ATAC&lt;/strong> are that:&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>The -O (--overlap) Option of Cutadapt</title><link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2023-12-10-the-o-option-in-cutadapt/</link><pubDate>Mon, 11 Dec 2023 15:07:53 +0800</pubDate><guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2023-12-10-the-o-option-in-cutadapt/</guid><description>&lt;p>In recent years, I noticed one problem about the ATAC-seq/scATAC-seq experiments we did in the lab. Specifically, it is related to the ATAC-seq insert size, or fragment length, plotting. The distribution of the fragment length in an ATAC-seq experiment is an important quality control metric. Since the transposase Tn5 can only go to those nucleosome-free regions, the lengths of the fragments after Tn5 transposition often exhibit a nucleosomal ladder pattern, like shown in &lt;a href="http://localhost:1313/posts/2017-02-10-atac-seq-insert-size-plotting/">&lt;strong>this post&lt;/strong>&lt;/a> where I described how to draw the plot by looking at the 9th column of the aligned SAM/BAM file.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>ATAC-seq Peak Calling With MACS2</title><link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2020-12-09-atac-seq-peak-calling-with-macs2/</link><pubDate>Wed, 09 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate><guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2020-12-09-atac-seq-peak-calling-with-macs2/</guid><description>&lt;p>Although &lt;strong>&lt;a href="http://www.nature.com/nmeth/journal/v10/n12/full/nmeth.2688.html">ATAC-seq&lt;/a>&lt;/strong> has been extensively used in the functional genomics field to study chromatin accessibility, it is still under debate how we should perform peak calling to identify oepn chromatin regions. &lt;a href="https://github.com/macs3-project/MACS">MACS2&lt;/a> is a very popular peak caller for ChIP-seq, and it has been used for ATAC-seq as well. How should we perform ATAC-seq peak calling using MACS2? That is a recurring question. If you pay attention to the details in those publications that uses ATAC-seq, you might notice that some people uses the &lt;code>--shift -100 --extsize 200&lt;/code> flags during MACS2 peak calling.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>ATAC-seq Insert Size Plotting</title><link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2017-02-10-atac-seq-insert-size-plotting/</link><pubDate>Fri, 10 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate><guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2017-02-10-atac-seq-insert-size-plotting/</guid><description>&lt;p>ATAC-seq is THE simplest genomic protocol to profile open chromatin regions in the genome. The original publication (&lt;strong>&lt;a href="http://www.nature.com/nmeth/journal/v10/n12/full/nmeth.2688.html">Nature Methods 10, 1213-1218&lt;/a>&lt;/strong>) has been cited 441 times at this moment of writing (1,073 times at this moment of re-posting). It has become almost a routine for a lab that is interested in transcriptional regulation.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>One common QC for the data is to plot the fragment size density of your libraries. The successful construction of a ATAC library requires a proper pair of Tn5 transposase cutting events at the ends of DNA. In the nucleosome-free open chromatin regions, many molecules of Tn5 can kick in and chop the DNA into small pieces; around nucleosome-occupied regions, Tn5 can only access the linker regions. Therefore, in a normal ATAC-seq library, you should expect to see a sharp peak at the &amp;lt;100 bp region (open chromatin), and a peak at ~200bp region (mono-nucleosome), and other larger peaks (multi-nucleosomes). Examples from one of my data:&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>