<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Latex on Not A Rocket Scientist</title><link>http://localhost:1313/tags/latex/</link><description>Recent content in Latex on Not A Rocket Scientist</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-gb</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 08 Feb 2025 09:07:53 +0800</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/latex/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Work Syncing Across Different Operating Systems</title><link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2025-02-08-work-syncing-across-different-oss/</link><pubDate>Sat, 08 Feb 2025 09:07:53 +0800</pubDate><guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2025-02-08-work-syncing-across-different-oss/</guid><description>&lt;p>I haven&amp;rsquo;t really used &lt;strong>Windows&lt;/strong> since 2012 when I switched from Windows 7 to &lt;strong>Mac OS&lt;/strong>. In recent years, I occasionally found myself in a situation where I had to use Windows for certain admin-related stuff. On top of that, I recently came across &lt;a href="https://www.gog.com/en/">GOG&lt;/a> that prompted me to play some classic PC games from the old days. Therefore, I built a PC and installed Windows 11. The user experience of Windows 11 so far was not really great for me. I&amp;rsquo;m okay with this, because I&amp;rsquo;m still mainly using my Mac computers. Currently, I have an iMac at work, a MacBookPro laptop and a Windows PC at home.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>A Brief But Comprehensive Book About TikZ and PGFPLOTS</title><link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-12-20-a--brief-but-comprehensive-book-about-tikz-and-pgfplots/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 09:07:53 +0800</pubDate><guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-12-20-a--brief-but-comprehensive-book-about-tikz-and-pgfplots/</guid><description>&lt;p>Earlier this year, I started a new GitHub repository called &lt;a href="https://github.com/dbrg77/TikZ_and_PGFPLOTS_draw">TikZ_and_PGFPLOTS_draw&lt;/a> where I used &lt;a href="https://tikz.dev/">TikZ&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="https://pgfplots.sourceforge.net">PGFPLOTS&lt;/a> to draw vector graphics for scientific illustrations. Now I&amp;rsquo;m gradually learning and switching to &lt;a href="https://ipe.otfried.org/">Ipe&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="https://inkscape.org">Inkscape&lt;/a> for a more flexible and easier drawing experience. However, TikZ and PGFPLOTS are the two things that I use routinely, so I still want to practice my skills. Therefore, I have kept updating the repo whenever I want to draw some basic stuff.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Drawing Vector Graphics For Publication Figures</title><link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-02-14-drawing-vector-graphics-for-publication-figures/</link><pubDate>Wed, 14 Feb 2024 16:01:00 +0800</pubDate><guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-02-14-drawing-vector-graphics-for-publication-figures/</guid><description>&lt;p>To generate figures for publications, I often use &lt;a href="https://matplotlib.org">&lt;strong>matplotlib&lt;/strong>&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="https://seaborn.pydata.org">&lt;strong>seaborn&lt;/strong>&lt;/a> to prepare plots and save them in PDF format. Then I use &lt;strong>PowerPoint&lt;/strong> to arrange and organise them into a full figure. Like this one shown below:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="http://localhost:1313/images/2024-02-14/figure_examples.png" alt="">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Those panels (a - d) were individually generated using &lt;strong>matplotlib&lt;/strong> (except the genome browser track), saved as PDFs and imported into one slide in &lt;strong>PowerPoint&lt;/strong>. The size of the slide can be set to conform to the requirements of the journal, but &lt;strong>A4 size&lt;/strong> generally works in almost all cases. Labels can be added manually in the &lt;strong>PowerPoint&lt;/strong> using a desired font. Once I&amp;rsquo;m satisfied, the whole slide can be exported to a PDF, which serves as a figure. We can do this for every figure. In this way, it is easy and straightforward to generate publication-ready figures and they are still in vector format and all the elements can be edited by other programs like &lt;a href="https://inkscape.org">&lt;strong>Inkscape&lt;/strong>&lt;/a> or &lt;strong>Illustrator&lt;/strong>.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>3D Visualisation of The Residual Sum of Squares</title><link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2023-07-10-3d-visualisation-of-the-residual-sum-of-squares/</link><pubDate>Mon, 10 Jul 2023 16:01:00 +0800</pubDate><guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2023-07-10-3d-visualisation-of-the-residual-sum-of-squares/</guid><description>&lt;p>I recently came across the video &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/my3lsV-VQjs">The Beauty of Linear Regression (How to Fit a Line to your Data)&lt;/a> by &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/@RichBehiel">Richard Behiel&lt;/a>. The video is very inspiring! It illustrates the relationship between the residual sum of squares and the slope and intercept. The visualisation is intuitive and beautiful. I want to do a similar and simpler thing in the lecture slides for a course.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In the video, the residual sum of squares was shown as a heatmap and the arrows were used to represent the negative gradients. Here I just want to use a Z-axis to represent the residual sum of squares, such that I have:&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Matplotlib With The Beamer Metropolis Style</title><link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2022-03-02-matplotlib-with-the--beamer-metropolis-style/</link><pubDate>Wed, 02 Mar 2022 10:49:27 +0800</pubDate><guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2022-03-02-matplotlib-with-the--beamer-metropolis-style/</guid><description>&lt;p>Ever since I came across the &lt;a href="https://github.com/matze/mtheme">metropolis&lt;/a> theme of &lt;a href="https://ctan.org/pkg/beamer">Beamer&lt;/a> two years ago, I always used that theme to prepare presentation and lecture slides whenever possible. I really like the design. The style is hard to resist. One problem with it or with beamer in general is that plotting is difficult and limited. I know that &lt;a href="https://ctan.org/pkg/pgfplots">pgfplots&lt;/a> is very powerful, and you can do some pretty &lt;a href="https://texample.net/tikz/examples/all/">complicated plots&lt;/a> with it. I used it for routine basic plotting in Beamer, such as the box/scatter plot, the bar chart, the histogram. However, I&amp;rsquo;m not very proficient at it. For some plots with really large data files, it is better just use &lt;a href="https://matplotlib.org">matplotlib&lt;/a>. However, when I do that, I have another problem shown below:&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>