<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Primer3 on Not A Rocket Scientist</title><link>http://localhost:1313/tags/primer3/</link><description>Recent content in Primer3 on Not A Rocket Scientist</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-gb</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 17 May 2024 15:07:53 +0800</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/primer3/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>ChIP Primer Design</title><link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-05-17-chip-primer-design/</link><pubDate>Fri, 17 May 2024 15:07:53 +0800</pubDate><guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-05-17-chip-primer-design/</guid><description>&lt;p>When we study the functions of a gene of interest (&lt;strong>GOI&lt;/strong>), it is common to use a combination of &lt;strong>loss-of-function&lt;/strong> and &lt;strong>gain-of-function&lt;/strong> assays in a study. In the era of genomics, we often use &lt;strong>RNA-seq&lt;/strong> experiments to find out the affected genes when the level of the GOI is reduced, &lt;em>e.g.&lt;/em> siRNA, shRNA &amp;amp; degron, or elevated &lt;em>e.g.&lt;/em> over-expression. If the GOI is a &lt;strong>transcription factor (TF)&lt;/strong>, a special type of proteins that can specifically interact with DNA to regulate transcription, the natural question to ask is whether those affected genes are regulated directly by the TF. When we say &amp;ldquo;directly&amp;rdquo;, we often mean that the TF binds to the &lt;strong>regulatory elements&lt;/strong> of a gene and regulate the transcription of that gene. This is different to the situation where the TF affects the expression of some genes which in turn change the expressions of the genes that we see in the RNA-seq experiments. How do we do that? Again, in the era of genomics, we often use &lt;strong>ChIP-seq&lt;/strong>, which is really good at finding &lt;em>bona fide&lt;/em> genome-wide binding events of a TF in an unbiased manner.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>