<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Preprocessing on Not A Rocket Scientist</title><link>http://localhost:1313/tags/preprocessing/</link><description>Recent content in Preprocessing on Not A Rocket Scientist</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-gb</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 26 Jan 2024 10:07:53 +0800</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/preprocessing/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>How Difficult Is It To Start Your Single-cell Analysis As A Beginner</title><link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-01-18-how-difficult-is-it-to-start-your-single-cell-analysis-as-a-beginner/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 Jan 2024 10:07:53 +0800</pubDate><guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-01-18-how-difficult-is-it-to-start-your-single-cell-analysis-as-a-beginner/</guid><description>&lt;p>The title for this post is &amp;ldquo;&lt;strong>How Difficult Is It To Start Your Single-cell Analysis As A Beginner&lt;/strong>&amp;rdquo;. However, once I finished writing the post, the majority of the content is actually about &amp;ldquo;&lt;strong>Seurat and OSCA Installation On Freshly Installed Ubuntu/Debian/Fedora&lt;/strong>&amp;rdquo;. Oh well &amp;hellip; If you do not have time, just go to the final &lt;a href="#summary">&lt;strong>Summary&lt;/strong>&lt;/a> section to see the final results.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="introduction">Introduction&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>When I started my NGS analysis during my PhD, which was more than 10 years ago, one of the most difficult things was software installation. In many cases, you needed to do the following three magic steps:&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>The _alt Chromosomes In The Reference Genome</title><link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-01-05-the-alt-chromosomes-in-the-reference-genome/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Jan 2024 15:07:53 +0800</pubDate><guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-01-05-the-alt-chromosomes-in-the-reference-genome/</guid><description>&lt;p>Early this week, I was re-organising my bookmarks in the browser and I came across &lt;a href="https://lh3.github.io/2017/11/13/which-human-reference-genome-to-use">&lt;strong>this post&lt;/strong>&lt;/a> by Heng Li published more than 6 years ago. It reminded me one of the problem I faced ~10 years ago when I first started using the &lt;code>GRCh38/hg38&lt;/code> version of the human reference genome for RNA-seq analysis. Let&amp;rsquo;s have a look what the problem was.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Now if we go to the &lt;a href="https://hgdownload.soe.ucsc.edu/downloads.html">UCSC genome browser&lt;/a> to download the reference genome data, we see that there are a couple of options:&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>The -O (--overlap) Option of Cutadapt</title><link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2023-12-10-the-o-option-in-cutadapt/</link><pubDate>Mon, 11 Dec 2023 15:07:53 +0800</pubDate><guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2023-12-10-the-o-option-in-cutadapt/</guid><description>&lt;p>In recent years, I noticed one problem about the ATAC-seq/scATAC-seq experiments we did in the lab. Specifically, it is related to the ATAC-seq insert size, or fragment length, plotting. The distribution of the fragment length in an ATAC-seq experiment is an important quality control metric. Since the transposase Tn5 can only go to those nucleosome-free regions, the lengths of the fragments after Tn5 transposition often exhibit a nucleosomal ladder pattern, like shown in &lt;a href="http://localhost:1313/posts/2017-02-10-atac-seq-insert-size-plotting/">&lt;strong>this post&lt;/strong>&lt;/a> where I described how to draw the plot by looking at the 9th column of the aligned SAM/BAM file.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Single Cell Data Preprocessing</title><link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2022-09-06-single-cell-data-preprocessing/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 Sep 2022 22:35:53 +0800</pubDate><guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2022-09-06-single-cell-data-preprocessing/</guid><description>&lt;p>When I started my PhD back in 2009, the next generation sequencing (NGS) technologies had already been out there for a while. They were in the process of being adapted by many labs. My impression back then was that it was difficult to learn how exactly those methods worked. There were many reasons for that, and one of them was the need of the commercial kits for the library preparation. As a beginner, you kind of knew roughly what the kit was doing: end repair, A tailing, ligate the adapters to the fragments &lt;em>etc&lt;/em>. However, there were many missing details due to the black box nature of the kit. For example, what enzymes are used in each step? What are the oligo sequences? Are there any modifications on the oligos? Those things are critical to understand the method.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>