<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Python on Not A Rocket Scientist</title><link>http://localhost:1313/tags/python/</link><description>Recent content in Python on Not A Rocket Scientist</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-gb</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 16 Sep 2024 09:00:00 +0800</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/python/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Quarto With Hugo</title><link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-09-16-quarto-with-hugo/</link><pubDate>Mon, 16 Sep 2024 09:00:00 +0800</pubDate><guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-09-16-quarto-with-hugo/</guid><description>&lt;p>Very often, I need to write in a &lt;a href="https://ipython.org/notebook.html">Jupyter/IPython Notebook&lt;/a>-like style, where output is immediately shown after a block of code. In the past, I just copy pasted the code block, saved the output plot as image files and displayed them using the &lt;code>![](imagePath)&lt;/code> syntax in markdown or the figure shortcode of &lt;a href="https://gohugo.io">Hugo&lt;/a>. However, it becomes tedious when there are many blocks of code and plots, obviously. I need a better option.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>How Difficult Is It To Start Your Single-cell Analysis As A Beginner</title><link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-01-18-how-difficult-is-it-to-start-your-single-cell-analysis-as-a-beginner/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 Jan 2024 10:07:53 +0800</pubDate><guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-01-18-how-difficult-is-it-to-start-your-single-cell-analysis-as-a-beginner/</guid><description>&lt;p>The title for this post is &amp;ldquo;&lt;strong>How Difficult Is It To Start Your Single-cell Analysis As A Beginner&lt;/strong>&amp;rdquo;. However, once I finished writing the post, the majority of the content is actually about &amp;ldquo;&lt;strong>Seurat and OSCA Installation On Freshly Installed Ubuntu/Debian/Fedora&lt;/strong>&amp;rdquo;. Oh well &amp;hellip; If you do not have time, just go to the final &lt;a href="#summary">&lt;strong>Summary&lt;/strong>&lt;/a> section to see the final results.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="introduction">Introduction&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>When I started my NGS analysis during my PhD, which was more than 10 years ago, one of the most difficult things was software installation. In many cases, you needed to do the following three magic steps:&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>3D Visualisation of The Residual Sum of Squares</title><link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2023-07-10-3d-visualisation-of-the-residual-sum-of-squares/</link><pubDate>Mon, 10 Jul 2023 16:01:00 +0800</pubDate><guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2023-07-10-3d-visualisation-of-the-residual-sum-of-squares/</guid><description>&lt;p>I recently came across the video &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/my3lsV-VQjs">The Beauty of Linear Regression (How to Fit a Line to your Data)&lt;/a> by &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/@RichBehiel">Richard Behiel&lt;/a>. The video is very inspiring! It illustrates the relationship between the residual sum of squares and the slope and intercept. The visualisation is intuitive and beautiful. I want to do a similar and simpler thing in the lecture slides for a course.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In the video, the residual sum of squares was shown as a heatmap and the arrows were used to represent the negative gradients. Here I just want to use a Z-axis to represent the residual sum of squares, such that I have:&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>