<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Genomics on Not A Rocket Scientist</title><link>http://localhost:1313/tags/genomics/</link><description>Recent content in Genomics on Not A Rocket Scientist</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-gb</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 17 May 2024 15:07:53 +0800</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/genomics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>ChIP Primer Design</title><link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-05-17-chip-primer-design/</link><pubDate>Fri, 17 May 2024 15:07:53 +0800</pubDate><guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-05-17-chip-primer-design/</guid><description>&lt;p>When we study the functions of a gene of interest (&lt;strong>GOI&lt;/strong>), it is common to use a combination of &lt;strong>loss-of-function&lt;/strong> and &lt;strong>gain-of-function&lt;/strong> assays in a study. In the era of genomics, we often use &lt;strong>RNA-seq&lt;/strong> experiments to find out the affected genes when the level of the GOI is reduced, &lt;em>e.g.&lt;/em> siRNA, shRNA &amp;amp; degron, or elevated &lt;em>e.g.&lt;/em> over-expression. If the GOI is a &lt;strong>transcription factor (TF)&lt;/strong>, a special type of proteins that can specifically interact with DNA to regulate transcription, the natural question to ask is whether those affected genes are regulated directly by the TF. When we say &amp;ldquo;directly&amp;rdquo;, we often mean that the TF binds to the &lt;strong>regulatory elements&lt;/strong> of a gene and regulate the transcription of that gene. This is different to the situation where the TF affects the expression of some genes which in turn change the expressions of the genes that we see in the RNA-seq experiments. How do we do that? Again, in the era of genomics, we often use &lt;strong>ChIP-seq&lt;/strong>, which is really good at finding &lt;em>bona fide&lt;/em> genome-wide binding events of a TF in an unbiased manner.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>How Difficult Is It To Start Your Single-cell Analysis As A Beginner</title><link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-01-18-how-difficult-is-it-to-start-your-single-cell-analysis-as-a-beginner/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 Jan 2024 10:07:53 +0800</pubDate><guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-01-18-how-difficult-is-it-to-start-your-single-cell-analysis-as-a-beginner/</guid><description>&lt;p>The title for this post is &amp;ldquo;&lt;strong>How Difficult Is It To Start Your Single-cell Analysis As A Beginner&lt;/strong>&amp;rdquo;. However, once I finished writing the post, the majority of the content is actually about &amp;ldquo;&lt;strong>Seurat and OSCA Installation On Freshly Installed Ubuntu/Debian/Fedora&lt;/strong>&amp;rdquo;. Oh well &amp;hellip; If you do not have time, just go to the final &lt;a href="#summary">&lt;strong>Summary&lt;/strong>&lt;/a> section to see the final results.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="introduction">Introduction&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>When I started my NGS analysis during my PhD, which was more than 10 years ago, one of the most difficult things was software installation. In many cases, you needed to do the following three magic steps:&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>ATAC-seq Peak Calling With MACS2</title><link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2020-12-09-atac-seq-peak-calling-with-macs2/</link><pubDate>Wed, 09 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate><guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2020-12-09-atac-seq-peak-calling-with-macs2/</guid><description>&lt;p>Although &lt;strong>&lt;a href="http://www.nature.com/nmeth/journal/v10/n12/full/nmeth.2688.html">ATAC-seq&lt;/a>&lt;/strong> has been extensively used in the functional genomics field to study chromatin accessibility, it is still under debate how we should perform peak calling to identify oepn chromatin regions. &lt;a href="https://github.com/macs3-project/MACS">MACS2&lt;/a> is a very popular peak caller for ChIP-seq, and it has been used for ATAC-seq as well. How should we perform ATAC-seq peak calling using MACS2? That is a recurring question. If you pay attention to the details in those publications that uses ATAC-seq, you might notice that some people uses the &lt;code>--shift -100 --extsize 200&lt;/code> flags during MACS2 peak calling.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>