<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>illumina sequencing on Not A Rocket Scientist</title>
    <link>https://notarocketscientist.xyz/tags/illumina-sequencing/</link>
    <description>Recent content in illumina sequencing on Not A Rocket Scientist</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 23 Jul 2024 09:00:00 +0800</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://notarocketscientist.xyz/tags/illumina-sequencing/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Understanding The Chromap Summary File</title>
      <link>https://notarocketscientist.xyz/posts/2024-07-23-understanding-the-chromap-summary-file/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Jul 2024 09:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
      <guid>https://notarocketscientist.xyz/posts/2024-07-23-understanding-the-chromap-summary-file/</guid>
      <description>Background When talking about scATAC-seq data preprocessing, I guess the first method that most people choose is Cell Ranger ATAC. The 10x Genomics Single Cell ATAC kit is probably the most widely used commercial method for doing scATAC-seq, and Cell Ranger ATAC provides a very convenient way of converting the raw sequencing reads to some sort of count matrix for downstream in-depth analyses. The problems with Cell Ranger ATAC are that:</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PIPseq again - PIPseeker$^{\textmd{TM}}$ Barcode Translation</title>
      <link>https://notarocketscientist.xyz/posts/2024-06-11-pipseq-again-pipseeker-barcode-translation/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Jun 2024 09:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
      <guid>https://notarocketscientist.xyz/posts/2024-06-11-pipseq-again-pipseeker-barcode-translation/</guid>
      <description>In one of the post where we figured out the library structure of the PIPseq$^{\textmd{TM}}$ V3 chemistry last year, we left a cliffhanger about how the PIPseeker$^{\textmd{TM}}$ software from FluentBio performed the barcode &amp;ldquo;translation&amp;rdquo;. During the translation, an original cell barcode that consists of four parts of &amp;ldquo;sub-barcodes&amp;rdquo; (8 bp + 6 bp + 6 bp + 8 bp) got mapped to a 16-bp barcode.&#xA;The V3 data Using the species mixing data from the V3 chemistry mentioned in the previous post, we would end up with the following files in our working directory if we finished all procedures described in the previous post:</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PIPseq$^{\textmd{TM}}$ V4 Update</title>
      <link>https://notarocketscientist.xyz/posts/2023-07-02-pip-seq-v4-update/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Jul 2023 00:30:00 +0800</pubDate>
      <guid>https://notarocketscientist.xyz/posts/2023-07-02-pip-seq-v4-update/</guid>
      <description>NOTE: this post is just a slightly more detailed version of this Twitter thread.&#xA;Not very long after I wrote the series about guessing the library layout of PIP-seq, the raw data (FASTQ files) for the V4 chemistry were made available from the FluentBio website, which is really nice.&#xA;Now let&amp;rsquo;s have a look at what has been changed. The experimental procedures seem to remain the same. What about the library layout and barcodes?</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Guessing Library Structures (4) - PIP-seq V1prototype</title>
      <link>https://notarocketscientist.xyz/posts/2023-06-07-guessing-library-structures-4/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jun 2023 00:30:00 +0800</pubDate>
      <guid>https://notarocketscientist.xyz/posts/2023-06-07-guessing-library-structures-4/</guid>
      <description>Portal Guessing Library Structures (1) - Background Guessing Library Structures (2) - PIPseq$^{\textmd{TM}}$ V3 Guessing Library Structures (3) - PIP-seq V2 Guessing Library Structures (4) - PIP-seq V1prototype This is the fourth post, also the last, from a series where I use the recent PIP-seq data as an example to demonstrate the importance to use a common standard like seqspec to accompany sequencing reads submissions into public repositories.&#xA;The V1?</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Guessing Library Structures (3) - PIP-seq V2</title>
      <link>https://notarocketscientist.xyz/posts/2023-06-04-guessing-library-structures-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 04 Jun 2023 09:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
      <guid>https://notarocketscientist.xyz/posts/2023-06-04-guessing-library-structures-3/</guid>
      <description>Portal Guessing Library Structures (1) - Background Guessing Library Structures (2) - PIPseq$^{\textmd{TM}}$ V3 Guessing Library Structures (3) - PIP-seq V2 Guessing Library Structures (4) - PIP-seq V1prototype This is the third post from a series where I use the recent PIP-seq data as an example to demonstrate the importance to use a common standard like seqspec to accompany sequencing reads submissions into public repositories.&#xA;Some Notes In the previous post, we have figured out the library structure of many samples from the Clark2023 paper.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Guessing Library Structures (2) - PIPseq$^{\textmd{TM}}$ V3</title>
      <link>https://notarocketscientist.xyz/posts/2023-06-03-guessing-library-structures-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Jun 2023 09:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
      <guid>https://notarocketscientist.xyz/posts/2023-06-03-guessing-library-structures-2/</guid>
      <description>Portal Guessing Library Structures (1) - Background Guessing Library Structures (2) - PIPseq$^{\textmd{TM}}$ V3 Guessing Library Structures (3) - PIP-seq V2 Guessing Library Structures (4) - PIP-seq V1prototype This is the second post from a series where I use the recent PIP-seq data as an example to demonstrate the importance to use a common standard like seqspec to accompany sequencing reads submissions into public repositories.&#xA;An Initial Look The PIP-seq method was originally put on bioRxiv on 13 June 2022.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Guessing Library Structures (1) - Background</title>
      <link>https://notarocketscientist.xyz/posts/2023-05-28-guessing-library-structures-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 May 2023 14:46:00 +0800</pubDate>
      <guid>https://notarocketscientist.xyz/posts/2023-05-28-guessing-library-structures-1/</guid>
      <description>Portal Guessing Library Structures (1) - Background Guessing Library Structures (2) - PIPseq$^{\textmd{TM}}$ V3 Guessing Library Structures (3) - PIP-seq V2 Guessing Library Structures (4) - PIP-seq V1prototype This is the first post from a series where I use the recent PIP-seq data as an example to demonstrate the importance to use a common standard like seqspec to accompany sequencing reads submissions into public repositories.&#xA;What&amp;rsquo;s The Problem? There are many interesting questions we can ask, but to what extent can we investigate and do research on them?</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Single Cell Data Preprocessing</title>
      <link>https://notarocketscientist.xyz/posts/2022-09-06-single-cell-data-preprocessing/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Sep 2022 22:35:53 +0800</pubDate>
      <guid>https://notarocketscientist.xyz/posts/2022-09-06-single-cell-data-preprocessing/</guid>
      <description>When I started my PhD back in 2009, the next generation sequencing (NGS) technologies had already been out there for a while. They were in the process of being adapted by many labs. My impression back then was that it was difficult to learn how exactly those methods worked. There were many reasons for that, and one of them was the need of the commercial kits for the library preparation. As a beginner, you kind of knew roughly what the kit was doing: end repair, A tailing, ligate the adapters to the fragments etc.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Getting Index Reads From SRA</title>
      <link>https://notarocketscientist.xyz/posts/2022-07-26-getting-index-reads-from-sra/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Jul 2022 10:07:27 +0800</pubDate>
      <guid>https://notarocketscientist.xyz/posts/2022-07-26-getting-index-reads-from-sra/</guid>
      <description>A few month ago, I ranted about the FastQ files submission for data produced by complex genomic protocols. The main reason of the rant is that we tried to get some single cell data from SRA, and we really needed the cell barcodes for the data preprocessing and analysis. However, the cell barcodes are stored in the indexing reads where it seems impossible to get from the .sra file. Recently, I finally found a way of getting those information &amp;hellip; well &amp;hellip; at least for some studies.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>About FastQ Files Submission</title>
      <link>https://notarocketscientist.xyz/posts/2022-02-27-about-fastq-files-submission/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Feb 2022 10:07:27 +0800</pubDate>
      <guid>https://notarocketscientist.xyz/posts/2022-02-27-about-fastq-files-submission/</guid>
      <description>This post collects my thoughts about fastq files accumlated over the years, specifically focusing on what should be included during a submission. It is not about the format of fastq files. If you are not sure about the format, you can check the Wikipedia page and this excellent paper by Cock et al. that contains very deteiled information and the history about the fastq file.&#xA;Let&amp;rsquo;s first look at what you will get from a typical Illumina sequencing experiment.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Why do I like CUT&amp;RUN more than ChIP-seq</title>
      <link>https://notarocketscientist.xyz/posts/2018-10-23-why-do-i-like-cut-and-run-more-than-chip-seq/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
      <guid>https://notarocketscientist.xyz/posts/2018-10-23-why-do-i-like-cut-and-run-more-than-chip-seq/</guid>
      <description>Chromatin immunoprecipitation (ChIP) is one of the gold standards to study protein-DNA interaction in vivo. In 1984, John Lis&amp;rsquo; lab at Cornell invented the first ChIP method using UV to crosslink protein to DNA, and they used this approach to study the interaction of the RNA polymerase with specific genes (Gilmour and Lis, 1984). However, UV crosslinking causes DNA damage that makes cerntain downstream analysis, such as PCR, very difficult. Most people often choose to use another approach developed by Alexander Varshavsky&amp;rsquo;s lab later in 1988 at MIT, where they used formaldehyde for the crosslinking to study the histone-DNA interaction around the hsp70 gene (Solomon et al.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Project scg_lib_structs</title>
      <link>https://notarocketscientist.xyz/posts/2018-07-13-project-scg-lib-structs/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
      <guid>https://notarocketscientist.xyz/posts/2018-07-13-project-scg-lib-structs/</guid>
      <description>Being able to perform genomic studies on the material obtained from single cells is just awesome. In 2009, Tang et al. presented the first study of mRNA-seq from single cells (scRNA-seq). Two years later, Navin et al. successfully sequenced the genome of single cells. Ever since then, the field of single cell genomics is rapidly evolving and has proved to be powerful in many aspects of biology.&#xA;Many methods (mainly for scRNA-seq) are invented along the way, which is a good thing.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
