<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Statistics on Not A Rocket Scientist</title><link>http://localhost:1313/tags/statistics/</link><description>Recent content in Statistics on Not A Rocket Scientist</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-gb</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 10 Jul 2023 16:01:00 +0800</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/statistics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>3D Visualisation of The Residual Sum of Squares</title><link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2023-07-10-3d-visualisation-of-the-residual-sum-of-squares/</link><pubDate>Mon, 10 Jul 2023 16:01:00 +0800</pubDate><guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2023-07-10-3d-visualisation-of-the-residual-sum-of-squares/</guid><description>&lt;p>I recently came across the video &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/my3lsV-VQjs">The Beauty of Linear Regression (How to Fit a Line to your Data)&lt;/a> by &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/@RichBehiel">Richard Behiel&lt;/a>. The video is very inspiring! It illustrates the relationship between the residual sum of squares and the slope and intercept. The visualisation is intuitive and beautiful. I want to do a similar and simpler thing in the lecture slides for a course.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In the video, the residual sum of squares was shown as a heatmap and the arrows were used to represent the negative gradients. Here I just want to use a Z-axis to represent the residual sum of squares, such that I have:&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>How Did Gauss Derive The Normal Distribution</title><link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2023-01-27-how-gauss-derived-the-normal-distribution/</link><pubDate>Fri, 27 Jan 2023 00:10:00 +0800</pubDate><guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2023-01-27-how-gauss-derived-the-normal-distribution/</guid><description>&lt;p>I first came across with the normal distribution when I was 17 years old in high school. The &lt;strong>probability density function (PDF)&lt;/strong> is&lt;/p>
&lt;p>$$f_{\boldsymbol{X}}(x) = \cfrac{1}{\sqrt{2\pi}\sigma}\,e^{-\frac{(x-\mu)^2}{2\sigma^2}}$$&lt;/p>
&lt;p>where $\mu$ and $\sigma$ are the population &lt;strong>mean&lt;/strong> and &lt;strong>standard deviation&lt;/strong>, respectively.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Like most people when they first came across this function, the derivation of the function was not really introduced. Soon after that, we started to use it to calculate probabilities and other things. However, where does it come from? What&amp;rsquo;s the intuition of the function? Why are two of the most important constants $\pi$ and $e$ there? Those questions lingered in my brain ever since.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Benford's Law and RNA-seq</title><link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2020-02-27-benfords-law-and-rna-seq/</link><pubDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate><guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2020-02-27-benfords-law-and-rna-seq/</guid><description>&lt;p>More than two years ago, I started to watch videos from the YouTube channel &lt;strong>&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/user/numberphile/">Numberphile&lt;/a>&lt;/strong>. I came across &lt;strong>&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Benford%27s_law">Benford&amp;rsquo;s Law&lt;/a>&lt;/strong>, and I was amazed when I saw it on &lt;strong>&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=XXjlR2OK1kM">this video&lt;/a>&lt;/strong>. Basically, Benford&amp;rsquo;s Law is an observation about the relative frequency distribution of the first digits from real-world data sets, where the data span multiple orders of magnitude. Intuitively, we expect them to be uniformly distributed so that each digit (from 1 to 9) has a relative frequency around 1/9. However, it turns out that 1 is the most frequent digit, and 2 is the 2nd most frequent digit, and so on. Since people who fabricate data tend to make the distribution uniform, Benford&amp;rsquo;s Law can be used for fraud detection. After watching the Numberphile video, I immediately realised that RNA-seq data should follow Benford&amp;rsquo;s Law as well. In an RNA-seq sample, you always have lowly expressed genes and highly expressed genes, and their expression values span several orders of magnitude. Indeed, there are papers about using Benford&amp;rsquo;s Law to characterise patterns of gene expressions, such as &lt;strong>&lt;a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4979126/">this one&lt;/a>&lt;/strong> and &lt;strong>&lt;a href="https://www.mdpi.com/2073-4409/8/9/1004">this one&lt;/a>&lt;/strong>.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>